Your Highness,
세자
Armory Director, Yang Yi, has committed suicide by poison.
무고령 양의가 독을 마시고 자결했습니다
These 3 registrars are
이 세 사람은
all in charge of purchasing the repeating crossbows.
모두 쇠뇌 구매를 담당했던 자들입니다ㅇ
-My Lord! We realize our mistake! -We know our mistake!
대인, 잘못했습니다
My Lord, don't kill us!
대인, 살려 주십시오
Don't kill us!
저희를 살려 주십시오
Spare our lives!
목숨만은 살려 주십시오
We really don't know anything!
정말 아무것도 모릅니다
[Heir of Prince Jing'an, Xiao Sheng; courtesy name: Wuyi]
[정안왕세자, 소성 자, 무의]
My Lord, don't kill us!
대인, 제발 살려 주십시오
Spare us, My Lord!
목숨만은 살려 주십시오, 대인
My Lord.
대인
It was the Armory Director who took bribes from others.
무고령이 다른 이에게 뇌물을 받았습니다
We know nothing.
저희는 정말 아무것도 모릅니다
-Yes! -Spare us, My Lord!
- 맞습니다, 대인 - 목숨만 살려 주십시오
Spare us, My Lord!
대인, 살려 주십시오
Give me a name.
이름 하나만 대거라
I really don't know!
소신은 정말 모릅니다
It was all done by the Armory Director, Yang Yi!
전부 무고령 양의가 한 짓입니다
My Lord!
대인
My Lord, don't kill me!
대인, 살려 주십시오
You are quite lucky.
넌 운이 좋구나
Still won't talk?
이래도 말하지 않을 테냐?
It's... It's Prince Changsha!
장, 장사왕입니다
Very good.
좋다
My Lord.
대인
Please don't kill me!
살려 주십시오
My Lord, don't kill me!
대인, 살려 주십시오
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[작골]
[Episode 1]
[제1화]
Your Highness, the Valiant Cavalry has been completely wiped out.
세자, 효기영이 전멸하고
The Northern Qin's Army is pressing on the border.
북진의 대군이 몰려오고 있습니다
The Eagle King has started to attack the city!
응왕이 이미 성을 공격하기 시작했습니다
Change into armor!
갑옷을 가져와라
Zhang Ji, Feng Wu!
장적, 빙무
-Yes, Your Highness!
네
You two lead the death squad
너희 둘은 결사대를 이끌고
to secretly put fish oil, dry wood, and sulfur
어유, 마른 장작과 유황을
in the granaries and armories.
식량 창고와 무기고 곳곳에 매복하라
Once the enemy breaks into the city,
적군이 성을 함락하면
seal the gates and reduce everything to ashes.
성문을 봉쇄하고 성을 불태워 초토화해
Burn the entire Jiuzhang Plain.
구장원을 불바다로 만들어라
Please think twice, Your Highness.
세자, 다시 생각해 주십시오
You are the Beifu Commander.
세자께서는 북부의 총사령관이십니다
[Zhang Ji, Lieutenant General of Beifu Army]
[북부군 부장군, 장적]
If anything happens to you...
만약 세자께 무슨 일이라도 생기면...
If I don't act as bait,
내가 미끼가 되지 않으면
how can we lure the Eagle King's army into the city?
어찌 응왕의 군대를 성안으로 끌어들이겠느냐?
How else can we avenge the Valiant Cavalry?
또 어찌 억울하게 죽은 효기영들의 원수를 갚겠느냐
Where are the Beifu soldiers?
북부군 있느냐!
-Here!
있습니다!
Raise your wine.
술잔을 들어라!
-Yes!
네!
We are outnumbered by our enemy!
적은 많고 우리는 적다
Will you fight to the death with me?
나와 함께 죽을 각오가 되었느냐!
-We will!
되었습니다!
If we can't make it back...
죽어서 시신을 거두지 못한대도
-Then so be it!
그뿐이다!
Who says we stand alone?
어찌 옷이 없으랴
We share weal and woe.
그대와 전포를 함께 나누리라
Holding onto our brotherhood,
전우의 의리로
we face life and death together!
생사를 함께하자
It will be proven today.
바로 오늘
Fight!
싸워라!
-Fight! Fight! Fight!
싸우자, 싸우자, 싸우자!
[Jiuzhang Plain, Ye]
[대업, 구장원]
-Charge!
죽여라!
♪ Fight and let flames sweep the plains in darkness ♪
♪ 싸워라 어둠을 태워 버려라 ♪
♪ Still hot-blooded ♪
♪ 뜨거운 피는 아직 식지 않았다 ♪
♪ Our original intention won't change ♪
♪ 초심은 결코 변치 않아 ♪
♪ Fight to the bitter end ♪
♪ 싸워라, 승리하기 전엔 돌아서지 않으리 ♪
♪ My promises endure like a river ♪
♪ 한 번 한 맹세는 강물처럼 이어지고 ♪
♪ I dare you to challenge me ♪
♪ 거침없이 나아가니 누가 감히 막겠는가 ♪
♪ Listen, the winds begin to roar ♪
♪ 들어라, 바람이 일며 ♪
♪ The clash of arms rages on ♪
♪ 창칼이 한창 맞부딪히는구나 ♪
♪ Let flames sweep the plains in darkness ♪
♪ 어둠을 불태우며 ♪
♪ Still hot-blooded ♪
♪ 뜨거운 피는 아직 식지 않았다 ♪
♪ Fight and let flames sweep the plains in darkness ♪
♪ 싸워라 어둠을 태워 버려라 ♪
♪ My promises endure like a river ♪
♪ 한 번 한 맹세는 강물처럼 이어지고 ♪
♪ I dare you ♪
♪ 거침없이 나아가리 ♪
Urgent military report from Jiuzhang Plain!
구장원에서 온 긴급 군보입니다!
[Jiankang, Ye]
[대업, 검강]
[Grand Tutor's Mansion]
[태부부]
Mrs. Bai,
백 부인
[Princess Yunzhao, Li Fuhua] [Mrs. Bai] [Mr. Bai]
[운소 군주, 이보화 백 부인, 백 공자]
Jiayu always sits in on classes at the Imperial Academy.
가어는 줄곧 태학에서 청강하여
She is quiet, gentle, graceful, and refined.
얌전하고 온화한 데다 품성도 훌륭한 아이입니다
Your Highness, is this what you meant by "quiet, gentle,
이게 군주께서 말씀하신 얌전하고 온화한
graceful, and refined"?
품성이 훌륭한 모습입니까?
Lin, let's go.
림아, 가자
-Let's go. -Mrs. Bai, please hold on.
- 가자 - 백 부인, 잠시만요
[Xie Jiayu, Grand Tutor Xie's daughter]
[사 태부의 딸, 사가어]
Mrs. Bai,
백 부인
Mr. Bai,
백 공자
I'd like to greet you.
가어, 인사드립니다
It's okay.
별말씀을요
I've long heard
예로부터
about Mr. Bai's handsome looks and talent.
백 공자께서 풍채가 뛰어나고 인물이 출중하시다 들었습니다
Seeing you today,
오늘 직접 뵈니
I realize it's indeed true.
과연 소문 그대로네요
What's wrong, Mr. Bai?
백 공자, 무슨 일이에요?
You look so pale.
안색이 이렇게 창백하시다니
Are you feeling unwell?
몸이 편찮으신가요?
-Lin! -Young Master! Young Master!
- 림아! - 공자!
Lin! Lin! Lin!
림아!
Who bought the konjac?
곤약은 누가 산 것이냐?
It was planted in the backyard.
뒷마당 밭에서 심은 거예요
What about the fish maw?
그럼 어교는?
It's what you left over last night, Mother.
어머니께서 어젯밤 드시고 남기신 겁니다
And what about the blood?
피는?
I used chicken blood to fake it.
닭피로 대신했습니다
So it doesn't look quite like human blood.
그래서 사람 피와 색이 좀 달라요
It's a bit darker.
색이 조금 검지요
Pig blood should work better next time.
다음엔 돼지 피를 쓰면 효과가 더 좋을 거예요
And this creepy hair?
그리고 귀신 분장에 쓴 머리카락은 또 뭐냐?
Mother, that's not hair.
어머니 그건 머리카락이 아니에요
It's from the tails of Lightning and Dilu.
그건 섬전과 적로의 꼬리예요
I only cut off this tiny bit.
조금만 잘랐어요
They are steeds bestowed by His Majesty!
그건 황제께서 하사하신 명마야
Don't worry, Mother. It will grow back.
어머니, 걱정하지 마세요 다시 자랄 겁니다
Cang'er!
창이
You not only let
아가씨가 철없이 구는데
the Young Lady mess around,
말리기는커녕
but also kept watch for her.
망까지 봐 줬단 말이냐?
[Cang'er]
[창이]
Guards!
여봐라!
Hold her down and beat her!
붙잡고 매우 쳐라!
Today, I will let you know
오늘 내가 네게
what it means to turn a fake act into reality.
장난이 진짜가 되는 게 뭔지 똑똑히 알려주마
Please forgive me, Your Highness.
군주, 용서해 주십시오
Mother, just beat me if you want to beat someone.
어머니, 때리시려거든 저를 때리세요
Don't involve others in it.
다른 사람은 끌어들이지 마세요
But I've already told you, Mother,
하지만 저도 어머니께 분명히 말씀드렸잖아요
I only want Mao.
저는 무와 혼인을 할 거예요
Since you won't listen to me, Mother,
어머니께서 제 말을 듣지 않으시니
I won't listen to you, either.
서로 자기가 하고 싶은 대로 해요
That should be fair.
이래야 공평하죠
Marriage is
혼인은
determined by parents.
부모가 정하는 것이다
How can you decide it yourself?
네가 멋대로 정할 일이 아니다
Beat her!
매우 쳐라!
[Nanxing]
[남성]
Is this really Xiao Wuyi's coffin?
정말 소무의의 관이야?
No way. How could a figure like Young Lord Xiao
설마요 소 세자 같은 분이
die in battle so easily?
그렇게 쉽게 전사하시겠어요?
No matter how good Xiao Wuyi is at fighting,
소무의가 아무리 전쟁에 능해도
he is still human.
결국 사람 아니겠어?
[Xie Huaigui, Grand Tutor of Southern Ye]
[남업 태부, 사회귀]
Look at this coffin.
저 관을 봐
It's a specification that only a prince can use.
왕작을 받은 사람만 쓸 수 있는 규격이야
If it's not Xiao Wuyi, who else could it be?
소무의가 아니면 누구겠어?
But how could Jiuzhang Plain be seized by others?
그런데 구장원에서 어쩌다 패한 거죠?
All because Xiao Wuyi thought he was smart.
소무의가 똑똑한 척하다가 화를 자초한 거지
Do you know any inside information, bro?
형님 무슨 내막이라도 있습니까?
-Greetings, Grand Tutor.
태부를 뵙습니다
Speak and act cautiously.
언행을 조심하고
Do not discuss state affairs.
국사를 함부로 논하지 마라
-Yes.
명심하겠습니다
Master, please save Lady Jiayu.
주군 어서 아가씨를 구해주세요
If you don't go back, her life will be in danger!
더 늦으면 아가씨 목숨이 위태롭습니다
Okay, hurry.
알았다, 어서 가자
Stop, stop.
그만둬라, 그만
Go, go away.
다들 물러나거라
It must have hurt so much!
많이 아프지?
Father,
아버지
you are finally back.
드디어 오셨네요
Darling, no matter how angry you were,
부인, 아무리 화가 났어도
you shouldn't have beaten her like this.
이렇게 때리면 안 되오
After all, Yao Yao is a girl.
아무리 그래도 요요는 여식 아니오
Father...
아버지
Your good daughter
당신의 귀한 딸이
trimmed the tails of your two beloved horses.
당신이 아끼는 말 두 필의 꼬리를 잘랐어요
My... My...
내, 내...
M-My...
나, 나의...
Dilu?
적로가...
Father.
아버지
It hurts.
아파요...
It really hurts.
너무 아파요
Isn't it just a horse?
고작 말 한 필이잖소
You still shouldn't have beaten her.
그래도 때리면 안 되오
When has she ever taken a beating honestly?
언제 얌전히 맞은 적이 있다고 그래요?
Why didn't you tie the cushion today?
오늘은 왜 방석을 대지 않았느냐?
She didn't tie the cushion?
방석을 안댔다고?
Nanxing, fetch the physician quickly!
남성, 어서 의원을 모셔라
Yes, Madam.
예
Are you trying to infuriate me to death?
이 계집애가 날 속 터져 죽게 할 셈이냐?
Since you didn't tie the cushion,
방석을 대지도 않았으면서
why didn't you cry out when you were beaten?
왜 맞으면서 울지도 않았느냐?
You don't care about me anyway, Mother.
어차피 어머니는 저를 안 아끼시잖아요
So crying out was pointless.
울고 소리쳐도 소용없어요
If beating me could make you feel better, Mother,
절 때려야 어머니 화가 풀리신다면
I'd just let you beat me.
때리세요
I could endure it.
전 견딜 수 있어요
Darling,
부인
Yao Yao knows she is wrong.
요요가 잘못했다고 하잖소
She won't dare to do it ever again.
다시는 그러지 않을 것이오
You always spoil her.
당신이 늘 감싸고도니
That's why she is so unruly now.
애가 이렇게 안하무인이 된 거예요
I'm anxious to arrange a marriage for her just because...
내가 서둘러 혼처를 찾으려는 것도...
Forget it.
됐어요
I can't discipline you anymore.
이젠 나도 널 못 가르치겠다
Let the Xies' ancestors educate you.
사씨 가문 조상님들께 배우거라
Go reflect on your mistakes at the ancestral hall.
사당에 가서 반성해
Copy the "Book of Rites" 100 times.
'예기'를 백 번 베껴라
You are not allowed to come out until you finish.
다 베끼기 전엔 나오지 마
Yes, copy.
베끼겠다고 해, 어서
Mother, I will do it.
어머니, 할게요
I will copy it 100 times.
백 번 베낄게요
Your Highness,
군주
Prince Changsha is here.
장사왕께서 오셨습니다
Prince Changsha?
장사왕?
Stay put here and behave yourself.
얌전히 안에 있어
Don't come out.
절대 나오지 마라
Your Highness, what are these?
전하, 이것들은...
[Prince Changsha]
[장사왕]
Betrothal gifts, of course.
혼수 예물입니다
I have admired Jiayu for a long time.
나는 오래전부터 가어를 마음에 두고 있어
So I specifically came to deliver the betrothal gifts today.
오늘 특별히 예물을 가지고 왔습니다
Where is Jiayu?
가어는 어디 있습니까?
Jiayu!
가어
-Jiayu? -Your...
- 가어 - 전, 전하
Your Highness, you must be joking.
농이 지나치십니다
Jiayu is still young.
가어는 아직 어립니다
She is not in a hurry to get married.
아직 혼인시킬 생각은 없습니다
Why did I hear that Her Highness has recently
그런데 듣자 하니 군주께서 요즘
been looking for a marriage match for Jiayu?
가어의 혼처를 알아보고 계시다던데요
But unfortunately,
하지만 안타깝게도
Jiayu didn't take a liking to any of them.
가어 마음에 드는 이가 하나도 없었다죠
She even scared away
오늘도 백 공자마저
Young Master Bai today.
겁을 먹고 달아났다 들었습니다
So,
그러니까요
Jiayu is still too young
가어는 아직 어려
and immature.
철이 없습니다
I plan to keep her by my side
제 곁에 두고
and discipline her for a few more years.
몇 년 더 가르칠 생각입니다
That would be even better.
그거야 더없이 좋지요
Your Highness, you carry on the late Empress Dowager's
군주의 예법은 선태후께서 몸소 가르치셨고
imperial demeanor.
황실의 품격을 고스란히 이으셨습니다
And the Grand Tutor, needless to say,
태부의 학문과 인품은 더 말할 것도 없지요
boasts the elegance of a noble family.
명문가의 풍모가 아닙니까
In the future, when Jiayu follows me into the palace,
훗날 가어가 나와 함께 입궁하면
she will surely impress the world as empress.
천하의 국모가 될 것입니다
Your Highness, the Xie family and I
전하, 사씨 가문와 저는
have no intention of sending Jiayu to the imperial palace.
가어를 입궁시킬 생각이 없습니다
It doesn't matter.
괜찮습니다
She is young,
가어가 아직 어리니
so you, my aunt, and the Grand Tutor can't bear to let her go.
고모님과 태부께서 쉽게 보내지 못하는 거겠지요
I can wait.
난 기다릴 수 있습니다
However, I
하지만 본왕은
also admire the Grand Tutor's talent and dignity.
태부의 학문과 고결한 인품을 늘 흠모해 왔습니다
In three days, at the Lantai gathering,
사흘 뒤 난대회에서
I will hold a poetry gathering at the Mid-Lake Pavilion.
호심정에서 시회를 열 예정입니다
Grand Tutor, I'll be
그때 태부께서 오셔서
waiting for you to give your guidance on poetry.
시문을 지도해 주시길 기다리겠습니다
Farewell.
이만 가겠습니다
What an arrogant jerk.
오만한 놈
If the world falls into his hands,
천하가 저자의 손에 넘어가면
wouldn't the people be like living in hell?
백성들은 인간 지옥에서 살게 될 거예요
Prince Changsha has been forming factions,
장사왕은 세력을 넓히고
craving the support of noble families.
세가의 지지를 얻는 데만 혈안이 되어 있어요
If it weren't to win over you and the honest officials,
당신과 청류 세력을 끌어들이려는 게 아니었다면
he wouldn't have targeted Jiayu at all.
가어를 노리지도 않았을 거예요
It's my fault.
내 잘못이오, 내 잘못
I don't allow you to go to that poetry gathering.
그 시회인지 뭔지는 절대 가지 마세요
I didn't say I was going, Darling.
간다고 한 적도 없소, 부인
You are in such a hurry to arrange a marriage for Yao Yao,
당신이 그렇게 요요 혼사를 서두르지만
but she likes Mao.
요요는 무를 좋아하잖소
Prince Changsha is out of the question,
장사왕은 안 됩니다
and Prince Qi is even more so.
기왕은 더더욱 안 되고요
In view of Prince Changsha's eagerness,
장사왕이 저렇게 서두는 걸 보니
I'm afraid it will happen soon.
아마도 머지않았구나
You've started copying already?
벌써 베끼기 시작했구나
Father.
아버지
I brought you some food.
아버지가 먹을 걸 가져왔다
Thank you, Father.
고맙습니다, 아버지
I thought you were copying the book.
글만 베끼는 줄 알았더니
What are you designing now?
이번엔 또 뭘 꾸미는 게냐?
Father, lend me your jade crown.
아버지, 옥관 좀 빌려주세요
You're giving this jade crown to Mao?
이 옥관은 무에게 주려는 것이냐?
Mao left the capital on a mission for the Empress Dowager this time.
이번에 무가 태후마마를 대신해 경성을 떠나
He went to Qingyun Mountain to seek medical help and pray for His Majesty.
청운산으로 폐하를 위해 신의를 찾으러 갔어요
It is said that he found a miraculous doctor.
듣기로는 신의를 찾았다고 하더라고요
Then the Empress Dowager will definitely reward him.
그렇게 되면 태후마마께서 분명 상을 내리실 거예요
Mao said
무가 그러는데
that when the time comes, he will ask for a fief
그때 영지를 하나 구해서
and then come to propose to me.
청혼하러 오겠대요
This will be the most important day of his life.
이건 무 인생에서 가장 중요한 날이잖아요
I want to give him a jade crown,
옥관 하나 선물해서
so he can look his best on that day.
그날만큼은 누구보다 당당하고 멋진 모습이었으면 해서요
Why are you sighing, Father?
왜 한숨을 쉬세요?
I'm jealous.
질투가 나서 그런다
Jealous?
질투요?
I haven't even received
이 아비도 아직
a jade crown personally designed by my daughter,
딸이 직접 만든 옥관을 받아 보지 못했는데
but that boy beat me to it.
그 녀석이 먼저 받게 생겼잖니
Father!
아버지
Mao is the student you're most proud of.
무는 아버지께서 가장 아끼시는 제자잖아요
If you like it, Father,
아버지도 원하시면
when it's your birthday,
이제 생신 때
I'll buy a piece of fine jade and carve one for you myself.
좋은 옥을 사다가 직접 조각해 드릴게요
How about that?
어때요?
I don't need these things.
난 그런 건 필요 없다
I'll just be happy as long as you cause
네가 어머니랑 그만 좀 다투면
less trouble for your mother.
그걸로 만족이야
Come on, eat it while it's hot.
자, 식기 전에 먹어라
Okay.
네
My Lady, please get off.
아가씨, 내리십시오
My Lady, I really don't think I can do this.
아가씨 정말 안 될 것 같아요
Maybe I should just go back.
그냥 돌아가요
You can do this. Come on.
할 수 있어 넌 할 수 있다니까
Trust yourself.
자신을 믿어
-Let's go. -I can't.
- 가자 - 안 돼요
You are Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
당신이 묘수 공자예요?
Yes, it's me.
네, 맞아요
I heard you two want to negotiate
두 분께서
a big deal worth 3,000 taels of silver.
삼천 냥짜리 큰 거래를 하신다던데
What exactly do you want to buy?
대체 뭘 만들려는 거죠?
Young Master of Miraculous Craft,
묘수 공자는
can you really make anything?
정말 뭐든 만들 수 있나요?
Of course.
물론이죠
From flying wooden kites
하늘을 나는 목연부터
to waterwheels for drawing water,
물을 퍼 올리는 수차까지
as long as it's a mechanical device,
기발한 기계 장치라면
there is nothing I...
저...
There's nothing our Young Lady can't make.
저희 아가씨께서 못 만드시는 건 없어요
Three feet long, weighing sixteen taels,
길이 석 자에 무게는 열여섯 냥
portable,
몸에 지닐 수 있고
a repeating crossbow that shoots four arrows at once.
화살 네 발을 연달아 쏘는
Can you make it?
쇠뇌도 만들 수 있나요?
What?
왜 그러시죠?
Are you stumped?
어려운가요?
What do you need
공자께서는
this item for, sir?
그걸 어디에 쓰시려는 건가요?
It's a gift.
선물할 겁니다
It's a weapon of slaughter.
사람을 죽이는 물건을
Who would dare to receive such a gift?
누가 선물로 받아요?
Why do you care so much?
그런 건 신경 쓰지 마세요
Just tell me if you can make it.
만들 수 있는지 없는지만 말하세요
I can't.
못 해요
You're lying!
거짓말!
My younger brother likes to hunt wild bears.
아우가 들곰 사냥을 좋아해서요
We heard that you can make a four-shot repeating crossbow,
네 발 연발로 쏠 수 있는 쇠뇌를 만드신다기에
so we came here for it.
소문을 듣고 찾아왔습니다
Three thousand taels of silver. The price is negotiable.
삼천 냥입니다 값은 더 얘기해 볼 수 있고요
If you like hunting,
공자께서 사냥을 즐기신다면
Young Master of Miraculous Craft has other mechanisms.
묘수 공자에게 다른 물건도 있습니다
This Whistling Arrow can drive away wolves at night.
이 향운전은 밤에 늑대를 쫓을 수 있고
And these Nine-Linked Rings
이 구련환은
can be used either as a trap
함정으로도 쓸 수 있고
or as a lock.
자물쇠로도 쓸 수 있죠
This Breezing Powder...
이 영풍산은...
Enough.
됐습니다
I don't want any of these.
그런 건 다 필요 없어요
I just want the repeating crossbow.
난 연발로 쏠 수 있는 쇠뇌만 있으면 됩니다
I can make it, but I won't.
만들 순 있지만 만들어 드릴 순 없어요
Why?
왜죠?
This three-feet, four-arrow repeating crossbow
이 삼척사전 쇠뇌는
was custom-made for a buyer.
특정 손님만을 위해 맞춤 제작한 물건이에요
It was agreed that it could only be sold to him.
처음부터 그분께만 팔기로 약속했죠
Being merchants, we must keep our word.
장사꾼은 신의를 지켜야 하니까요
No matter how much you pay me,
아무리 돈을 많이 주셔도
Young Master
이 거래는
of Miraculous Craft still won't take this deal.
묘수 공자는 받을 수 없어요
You are the real Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
당신이 묘수 공자였군요
Tell me who that buyer is.
말해요, 구매자가 누구죠?
Will you let us go
말하면
if I tell you?
저희를 보내주실 건가요?
If you tell me, you'll suffer less.
말하면 고생은 덜 하게 해주죠
Creating such a harmful thing, you
이런 흉악한 물건을 만들다니
deserve to die.
죽어 마땅해요
Fine.
알겠어요
Don't you just want a name?
이름 하나 알려달라는 거잖아요
I'll tell you.
말해드리죠
Say it!
어서 말해요
He said his surname is
성은...
Xiao.
소
Xiao?
소?
And his given name is Sheng.
이름은 외자 성이라고 했어요
What?
뭐라고요?
Xiao Sheng?
소성?
Jump!
뛰어!
I don't dare.
못 뛰겠어요!
Stop there!
거기 서요!
It's too late.
늦었어
Toys!
재밌는 물건
Come and take a look!
구경하세요
Fortunately, I was prepared,
미리 준비해서 다행이야
and asked you to switch carriages to pick me up.
일부러 다른 마차로 마중 나오라고 한 거야
[Li Lejun, Princess Pingning]
[평녕 현주, 이악군]
You knew it was a trap.
함정인 걸 알면서
Why did you still take the risk?
왜 위험을 무릅쓴 거야?
I was just trying to make money.
돈 벌려고 그랬지
The monthly allowance my mother gives me
어머니가 주시는 용돈으론
is nowhere near enough to make a jade crown for Mao.
무한테 옥관 만들어 주기엔 턱없이 부족하거든
It's just a pity to lose such a big deal.
큰 거래를 놓친 게 아깝긴 해
As expected, there's no such thing as a free lunch.
역시 세상에 공짜는 없어
I just don't know
근데 이 소성이라는 자는
who Xiao Sheng is.
대체 정체가 뭐고
What kind of trouble did he stir up
무슨 짓을 했길래
to bring people to me, Young Master of Miraculous Craft?
묘수 공자까지 찾아온 거지?
I hope he didn't shoot anyone.
설마 누구를 쏘기라도 한 건 아니겠지?
You don't know who he is,
상대가 누군지도 모르면서
yet you dared to sell it?
팔았단 말이야?
He had money, and I had the goods.
그쪽은 돈이 있고 난 물건이 있는데
Why should I care about who he is?
정체가 뭐든 무슨 상관이야?
By the way.
맞다
It's the letter my brother wrote to you.
오라버니가 보낸 편지야
When is Mao returning to the capital?
무는 언제 경성으로 돌아온대?
You say it.
네가 말해
We underestimated the enemy.
저희가 방심했습니다
We didn't expect Young Master of Miraculous Craft to be a woman.
묘수 공자가 여인일 줄은 몰랐습니다
She threw some weird gadgets at us
별 희한한 물건까지 던져대서
and got away.
결국 놓쳤습니다
She also said the one who bought the repeating crossbows i-is Xiao Sheng.
그리고 쇠뇌를 산 자가 소성이라고 했습니다
Xiao Sheng?
소성?
Me?
내가?
It must've been Prince Changsha
분명 장사왕이
intentionally using your name, Your Highness.
일부러 세자의 이름을 사칭한 겁니다
Rest assured, Your Highness.
세자, 안심하십시오
No matter what it costs,
땅을 뒤집어서라도
I will find this woman
소인이 그 여인을 찾아내
and get solid proof of her collusion with Prince Changsha.
장사왕과 공모했다는 확실한 증거를 잡겠습니다
But I feel like
하지만 소인이 보기엔
she doesn't seem to be in cahoots
그 여인은 장사왕과
with Prince Changsha.
한패 같지는 않습니다
Do you have any evidence?
증거는?
It's just a feeling.
느낌이야
Your Highness, this is what she dropped.
세자 그 여인이 떨어뜨린 것입니다
This is an official tribute satin.
이건 관제 공단이야
It's specifically made by the imperial court.
황실에서 하사하는 물건이라
Only the female relatives of noble families can have it.
명문가 규수가 아니면 가질 수 없지
Is there a record in the Household Department's archives?
소부의 장부에 명단이 있나?
So what if there is?
있으면 뭐 해?
With so many noble female relatives,
명문가 규수가 한둘도 아니고
are we supposed to ask them one by one?
집집이 찾아가서 물어보기라도 할 거야?
How's the investigation on Prince Changsha?
장사왕은 어찌 되었느냐?
As our spies reported last night,
어젯밤 첩자의 보고에 따르면
Prince Changsha will hold a poetry gathering at the Lantai gathering.
장사왕이 난대회에서 시회를 열어
He's invited lots of officials,
대신들을 모두 초청해
claiming it's to review the world's poems.
천하의 시문을 품평하겠다고 합니다
But he just wants to use the chance to win over the officials.
이 기회에 대신들을 포섭하려는 속셈이겠죠
He really thought you died in battle, Your Highness.
세자께서 정말 전사하신 줄 아나 봅니다
Lantai gathering?
난대회라...
This is a great opportunity for the young masters and ladies
명문가 자제들과 규수들이
of noble families to size each other up.
배필을 찾는 자리이기도 하지
Maybe Young Master of Miraculous Craft will attend it, too.
묘수 공자도 올지 모르니
We can just go join the fun.
우리도 가서 구경이나 하자꾸나
By the way, is there any news from Yongzhou?
참, 옹주 쪽은 소식 있느냐?
Have you found Armory Director Yang Yi's family?
무고령 양의의 가족은 찾았느냐?
Not yet.
아직입니다
I think he will definitely like
네가 만든 거라면
everything designed by you.
분명 다 좋아하실 거야
That's true. I've spent a lot of time designing it.
그렇지? 내가 오래 공들여 만든 거니까
Greetings, Your Highness.
군주를 뵙습니다
Mother.
어머니
No need for formalities, Lejun.
악군 그리 예를 갖출 필요 없다
Where have you been all day?
하루 종일 어디를 쏘다녔느냐?
I went to Prince Qi's Mansion to find Lejun, of course.
당연히 기왕부에 악군을 찾으러 갔죠
And I
게다가
spent the whole day copying the "Book of Rites."
하루 종일 '예기'를 베껴 썼어요
My hands are so sore.
손이 다 아프다니까요
Really?
정말이냐?
Today...
오늘...
Jiayu was with me.
가어는 저와 함께 있었어요
Your injuries haven't healed. Don't run around.
상처도 안 나았는데 돌아다니지 말거라
Once you're healed, go kneel in the ancestral hall.
다 나으면 사당에 가서 꿇어앉아라
Mother, I...
어머니, 저...
Don't think you can escape it.
넘어갈 생각 말거라
Mother,
어머니
can you take me to attend the Lantai gathering
모레 난대회에
the day after tomorrow?
저도 데려가 주시면 안 될까요?
When did I say I was going?
내가 언제 간다고 했느냐?
Don't you want to enjoy
경치도 좋다는데
that beautiful scenery, Mother?
어머니께선 구경하고 싶지 않으세요?
What are you plotting now?
또 무슨 꿍꿍이야?
Mother, you got me wrong.
어머니, 오해하셨어요
I just want to apologize to Mr. Bai.
백 공자께 사죄하고 싶어서요
After all, I was the one acting improperly that day.
그날은 제가 먼저 실례했잖아요
Whether the matchmaking worked or not,
혼담이 되든 안 되든
we shouldn't lose our manners.
예의는 지켜야죠
You can go to the Lantai gathering,
난대회에는 데려가주마
but no running around.
하지만 함부로 돌아다니지 말고
Apologize sincerely.
성의껏 사과해라
Don't worry, Mother.
어머니, 걱정하지 마세요
I promise I'll stick to you like glue.
어머니 허리띠에 딱 매달려 다닐게요
[Lantai gathering]
[난대회]
Let's go take a look ahead.
가자, 앞쪽도 구경해 보자
Mr. Bai, I offended you last time.
백 공자 지난번엔 제가 무례했습니다
Today, I'd like to apologize to you.
오늘 정식으로 사과드릴게요
Don't worry about it, Jiayu.
너무 격식 차릴 필요 없소
I also misunderstood last time.
지난번엔 제가 오해했소
This is my cousin.
이쪽은 제 사촌 동생이오
Nice to meet you.
반가워요
Nice to meet you, Miss Xie.
사 언니, 안녕하세요
Talk nicely with Mr. Bai.
백 공자와 이야기를 잘 나누렴
Remember not to run around.
절대 돌아다니면 안 된다
Do not go to the poetry gathering at the Mid-Lake Pavilion, whatever you do.
특히 호심정 시회엔 절대 가지 말거라
Please rest assured, Mother.
어머니, 걱정하지 마세요
I'm not interested in
시회니 뭐니
those poetry gatherings.
전 관심도 없어요
I wouldn't go even if they invited me.
불러도 안 갈 거예요
Come and take a look.
자, 구경하세요
Absolutely top-quality items.
전부 다 최상품입니다
Your fan is so beautiful.
이 부채 정말 예쁘네요
May I take a closer look?
잠깐 구경 좀 해도 될까요?
My cousin bought me this bamboo fan.
사촌오라버니가 사준 부채예요
It even has his inscription on it.
위에 오라버니께서 직접 글씨도 써주셨고요
It's the only one in the world.
세상에 단 하나뿐이죠
Mr. Bai's handwriting is really amazing.
글씨가 정말 멋지네요
If you want one, Jiayu,
원하시면
I'll write an inscription for you.
하나 써드리겠소
That's great!
정말요?
But I don't want an inscription on a fan.
그런데 저는 부채 말고
I want it on that celadon piece.
청자에다 써 주셨으면 좋겠어요
Here you are.
여기요
"The peach blossoms are in full bloom,
복사꽃이 만개하니...
brilliant..."
꽃...
Mr. Bai, you are truly amazing.
백 공자, 정말 대단하세요
Miss, I'll take this celadon.
주인장, 청자는 내가 사겠네
How much is it?
얼마지?
100 taels of silver.
백 냥입니다
100 taels of silver? Are you kidding me?
백 냥이라고, 완전 강도네
This is made from the clay of Mount Xi,
식산 흙으로 구운 데다
not to mention this gentleman's inscription.
이 공자의 글씨까지 있으니
It's unique in the world.
세상에 하나뿐입니다
No matter how great the inscription is,
어떤 대단한 글이라도
it's not worth this price.
이 정도로 비싸진 않아
Even Prince Qi's poems aren't worth 100.
기왕의 시문도 백 냥은 안 해
I don't want it anymore.
안 살래
What do you mean?
무슨 뜻이에요?
My cousin's poems are inferior to Prince Qi's?
우리 오라버니의 시문이 기왕만 못하다는 거예요?
Cousin.
동생
I mean, this seller is greedy.
주인장이 너무 비싸게 부른다는 뜻이에요
If I want it,
정말 갖고 싶으면
I'll just ask Mr. Bai
나중에 백 공자께
to write another one for me later.
다시 하나 부탁하면 되잖아요
Why waste money on it?
괜히 돈 낭비할 필요 없죠
Stingy.
인색하긴
Miss, I'll buy this celadon.
주인장 이 청자는 내가 사겠네
Okay.
좋아요
Hold on.
잠깐만요
You are right.
동생 말이 맞아요
I'm here to apologize today.
오늘은 내가 사과하러 온 거니까
I'll just force myself to buy this celadon.
이 청자는 내가 무리해서라도 사야겠어요
I already said I'd buy it.
내가 먼저 샀어요
I'll add another 50 taels of silver.
50냥 더 얹을게요
Two hundred taels.
2백 냥
Two hundred...
2백...
and one taels.
하고도 한 냥 더
Cousin, you...
사촌 동생, 너...
This celadon is mine now.
이 청자는 이제 내 거예요
There are really so many rich people.
부자들이 참 많네요
[The peach blossoms are in full bloom, brilliant]
[복사꽃이 만개하니 꽃...]
Mr. Bai,
백 공자
I'm afraid I'm meant to miss out
공자의 명필은
on your fine handwriting.
저와 인연이 없나 봐요
I want this pot.
이 호리병은 내가 사겠네
Okay.
알겠습니다
Nine-Turn Mind-Changing Pot!
구전회심호?
Jiayu, where are you going?
어디가시오?
Cousin, just leave that stingy person alone.
사촌 오라버니
Why is the Nine-Turn Mind-Changing Pot out for sale?
구전회심호를 왜 내다 판 거야?
Didn't you specifically
이것들은 전부
pick all these goods yesterday, My Lady?
어제 아가씨께서 직접 고르신 물건 아닌가요?
Oh, no.
큰일이야
I must have misplaced it.
내가 잘못 꺼내놨나 봐
Did you tell her how to poison with this pot?
독 쓰는 법은 말해줬어?
I explained how to use it once.
사용법은 한 번 설명했어요
Turn left for poison and right for wine.
왼쪽으로 돌리면 독이고 오른쪽으로 돌리면 술이라고요
She still bought it, knowing how to use the poison?
독 쓰는 법까지 알고 샀다고?
This person must be up to no good.
분명 꿍꿍이가 있어
I'll follow her and see.
따라가 봐야겠어
My Lady! Please don't run around!
아가씨 함부로 다니시면 안 돼요
Move out of the way! Move!
비켜라, 다 비켜!
Move!
저리 비켜, 비켜라!
Go away!
비켜!
Make way!
비켜라
Prince Changsha is here!
장사왕께서 오셨다
Move!
다 비켜!
Prince Changsha?
장사왕?
He's here for the poetry gathering, too?
장사왕도 시회에 왔어?
Can he compose poems?
저 사람도 시를 짓나?
Chan.
아선
I've made up my mind.
결심했어요
I'll put an end
오늘
to everything today.
끝을 낼 거예요
After the dance,
이따 춤이 끝나면
I'll curry favor with Prince Changsha.
난 장사왕의 총애를 청한 뒤
Then I'll drink this poisoned wine with him.
이 독주를 마시게 할 거예요
Sister,
언니
I'll take full responsibility for this.
이 일은 나 혼자 한 걸로 해요
It has nothing to do with anyone else.
다른 자매들과는 상관없어요
No,
아니야
we either live together
살아도 같이 살고
or die together.
죽어도 같이 죽어
How moving your sisterhood is.
정말 의리 깊은 자매들이군요
You want to kill Prince Changsha?
장사왕을 죽이려는 건가요?
Who are you?
당신은 누구죠?
You can't.
안 돼요
You want to expose us?
우릴 고발하려는 건가요?
I mean,
내 말은
this pot won't work.
이걸로는 안 된다고요
Although it was made of purple clay,
자사토로 만들긴 했지만
the kiln temperature wasn't high enough,
가마 온도가 낮아서
causing the body to crack
몸체가 갈라지고
and have a poor seal.
밀봉이 잘 안돼요
Now the pot's both sides contain poisoned wine.
지금 이 주전자는 양쪽 다 독주예요
If you drink it,
만약 이걸 마시면
you'll die, too.
당신도 죽게 될 거예요
How do you know?
당신이 그걸 어떻게 알죠?
Because I made this pot.
제가 만들었으니까요
Then we'll die together.
그럼 같이 죽는 거죠
Do you have to do it this way?
꼭 이래야만 하나요?
Is it worth it?
그럴 가치가 있어요?
Prince Changsha is a brutal tyrant.
장사왕은 포악해서
Every day, there are sisters who are tortured to death by him.
매일 자매들이 그 자에게 능욕을 당하다 죽어요
If I can exchange my life
오늘 내 목숨 하나로
for a way out for my sisters today,
자매들을 살릴 수 있다면
it's worth it.
가치가 있는 일이에요
If you dare to expose it,
감히 고발하면
I'll kill you first.
먼저 당신을 죽여버릴 거예요
Your Highness, the Grand Tutor is ill.
전하, 태부께서 편찮으셔서
[Wei Qianli, Household Department Adjutant] [Capital Prefect]
[소부 부승 위천리, 경조윤]
I'm afraid he can't make it today.
오늘은 못 오실 듯합니다
He just refuses to show respect to you, Your Highness.
분명 전하의 체면은 안중에도 없는 겁니다
[Chen Guangtong, Military Advisor]
[병조참군, 진광동]
He's a mere teacher. How dare he put on airs?
고작 글이나 가르치는 주제에 뭘 그리 잘난 척을 한답니까?
The Xie family is the head of the noble clans.
사씨 가문은 세가의 으뜸입니다
Although Grand Tutor Xie holds no court position,
사 태부께선 조정에 관직은 없으시지만
during the late Emperor's reign,
선제 때는
he once served at the center of the imperial government.
조정의 중추셨습니다
Now the court is full of the Xie family's disciples.
지금도 조정에는 사씨 문하생으로 가득합니다
They seem to have no faction,
파벌이 없는 듯해도
but their roots actually run deep
뿌리가 깊은 세력입니다
as the leader of the honest officials.
청류를 이끄는 인물이니
We cannot underestimate them.
절대 얕봐선 안 됩니다
Never mind.
됐다
Today, we only talk about bliss,
오늘 다른 얘기는 하지 말고
but not anything else.
좋은 얘기만 하자꾸나
Congratulations,
축하드립니다, 전하
Now that Xiao Wuyi is gone,
이제 소무의가 없으니
the Beifu Army is leaderless.
북부군은 머리 잃은 용이나 다름없습니다
I heard you are very good at painting and calligraphy.
자네가 서화에 조예가 깊다던데
Take a look at this painting for me.
이 그림 좀 봐주게
Your Highness,
전하
this painting is truly marvelous.
참 기묘한 그림입니다
With grand mountains
산도 있고
and waters,
물도 있고
it looks very authentic.
시원하게 탁 트인 느낌입니다
Nice.
좋다
Let's drink to our hearts' content today!
오늘은 취할 때까지 마시자
Play the music.
연주하라!
Go this way.
이쪽으로 가요
Where is this?
여긴 어디예요?
Don't worry.
걱정하지 마세요
I'm absolutely a good person.
난 절대 나쁜 사람이 아니에요
After you leave the Lantai gathering,
잠시 후 난대회를 빠져나가서
go to the blacksmith shop in the east of the city
성 동쪽에 있는 대장간으로 가요
and find a half-blind old woman.
눈이 반쯤 먼 할머니를 찾아가서
Tell her Young Master of Miraculous Craft sent you.
묘수 공자가 보냈다고 하면 돼요
She is really capable.
그분 실력이 대단하거든요
She can help you change your identities and leave the city.
신분을 바꿔
Let's go.
가요
But if Prince Changsha finds out about what you're doing,
하지만 장사왕에게 들키면
he won't let you go.
당신을 가만두지 않을 거예요
Don't worry, he can't do anything to me.
걱정하지 마세요 장사왕은 날 어쩌진 못해요
Hurry, let's go.
빨리 와요, 어서요
Keep up. All of you, keep up.
따라와요, 다들 어서 따라와요
Wait, what are you doing? Who are you?
뭐 하는 거야, 넌 누구냐?
Freeze!
움직이지 마세요
It's you.
당신이군요
Let go of me!
이거 놔요
What are you two up to?
뭐 하는 거예요?
Young Master of Miraculous Craft,
묘수 공자
I suppose you've been doing well.
오랜만이오
Who are you?
당신은 누구예요?
Don't move!
움직이지 마세요
Tell me
말하시오
which family's lady you are.
당신은 어느 집안 규수요?
Why should I tell you?
왜 알려줘야 하죠?
Fine.
상관없소
After I finish my business,
볼일을 다 보고 나면
I'll come back and take my time to deal with you.
돌아와서 천천히 손봐주겠소
You want to kill Prince Changsha,
장사왕을 죽이고 싶다고?
right?
그래?
What a coincidence.
마침 잘됐군
I have also been annoyed with him for a long time.
나도 그놈이 눈엣가시였거든
Take them away. Leave no one behind.
전부 데려가 하나도 남기지 마라
How do we leave?
왜 가는...
The Heir of Prince Jing'an has arrived!
정안왕 세자 납시오!
The Heir of Prince Jing'an?
정안왕 세자?
Isn't he dead?
죽은 거 아니었어?
Nice...
- 좋습니다 - 좋아요
Aren't you dead?
죽은 거 아니었어?
Were you exhilarated seeing
제 관이 성으로 들어오는 걸 보니
my coffin enter the city?
기분이 아주 좋으셨겠습니다
Did you really think I was dead?
제가 진짜로 죽은 줄 알았나 봅니다
As wise and mighty as you are, Your Highness,
세자께서는 영명하시고 신과 같은 무예를 지니셨으니
you wouldn't die.
죽으실 리 없습니다
So, which jerk spread the rumor
그럼 어느 자식이
that I died in battle in Jiuzhang Plain?
내가 구장원에서 전사했다고 떠든 거냐?
You?
너냐?
No?
아닙니다
Or you?
아니면 너인 것이냐?
Your Highness, I just ran into
오는 길에
some of your dancers on the way,
전하의 무희 몇을 만났는데
who were scheming to poison you,
전하를 독살하려 한다기에
so I brought them over to you.
직접 데려왔습니다
Thank you, Your Highness.
감사드립니다
Guards!
아무도 없느냐
But I like her temper.
하지만 본세자는 이런 성미가 마음에 드는데
I wonder if you can give her to me.
전하께서 양보해 주시겠습니까?
If you like her,
세자께서 마음에 드신다면
just take her away.
마음껏 데려가십시오
Since you're so generous, Your Highness,
전하께서 이리도 통이 크시니
why not also let me attend today's Lantai gathering?
오늘 난대회에 저도 한자리 끼워주시지요
Why did it suddenly
어째 내가 오자마자
become so quiet upon my arrival?
왜 이렇게 조용해진 거지?
Isn't it a poetry gathering today?
오늘 시회 아니었나?
Dance!
춤춰라
And compose poems.
시도 짓고
Adjutant Chen,
진 참군
you are famous for your poems in the capital.
경성에서 자네 시가 유명하다던데
Write one for me right now.
한 수 지어 보게
Your Highness, what kind of poem do you want?
무슨 시를 말씀입니까?
Compose a poem praising the battle in Jiuzhang Plain,
구장원 전투에서
where the Beifu Army reversed a losing battle
북부군이 역전승을 거두고
and killed the enemies heroically.
용맹하게 싸운 걸 찬양하는 시를 쓰게
I'm sorry, Your Highness.
죄송합니다, 세자
I don't know how to write poems.
소인은 시를 지을 줄 모릅니다
I can't do it for you.
도와드릴 수 없습니다
-He killed the man! -He killed him!
- 사람이 죽었다 - 사람이 죽었어
Are you crazy, Young Lord Xiao?
소 세자, 미쳤습니까?
How dare you kill an imperial official?
감히 조정의 명관을 살해하다니...
No one is allowed to leave.
아무도 나가지 마라
If you leave, how will you pay for the deaths of the 30,000 soldiers
가면 우리 북부군 3만 장병의 목숨값은
of my Beifu Army?
누가 갚을 셈이지?
Prince Changsha,
장사왕
he didn't know how to write poems.
저자는 시를 못 짓는다는데
Do you know how to write?
전하는 쓰실 줄 아십니까?
I don't believe you dare to kill me.
세자는 날 죽이진 못할 겁니다
He actually...
저자가...
He actually killed someone.
저자가 사람을 죽였어
People die in every battle.
전쟁터에서 사람을 안 죽이는 싸움도 있나요?
Fine.
상관없소
After I finish my business,
볼일을 다 보고 나면
I'll come back and take my time to deal with you.
돌아와서 천천히 손봐주겠소
Will he kill me later, too?
설마 이따가 날 죽이려는 건 아니겠지?
No, I have to run away quickly.
안 되겠다, 빨리 도망쳐야 해
Do none of you really know how to write poems?
정말 아무도 시를 못 짓는 건가?
I do!
소관이 할 줄 압니다
-Me, too! -I can also write!
- 저도 할 수 있습니다 - 저도 합니다
Continue the music and dance!
가무를 계속해라
Guys,
여러분
if this dance ends,
이 춤이 끝날 때까지
while the poem is not done,
시를 짓지 못하면
I will continue.
난 계속할 겁니다
I've finished writing.
다 썼습니다
I've finished writing, too!
- 소관도 다 썼습니다 - 저도 다 썼습니다
Me, too.
저도 다 썼습니다!
-Me, too. -I've also finished writing.
- 저도 썼습니다
Read it.
읽어라
Dedicated to Young Lord Xiao.
세자께 바칩니다
Not to me.
내가 아니라
Read it to Prince Changsha.
장사왕께 들려드려라
Cold frost flies...
'백 길 낭떠러지에‘
Read it loudly!
크게 읊어라
Cold frost flies over 1,000 feet.
'백 길 낭떠러지에 찬 서리 날리고'
Wuyi subdued tigers with his valour.
'무의의 위엄에 범도 엎드리네'
The army was drenched in enemy blood,
'군을 이끌어 오랑캐의 피를 마시고'
defending the country like a bright sun.
'나라를 지켜 성은을 입었네'
What a flattering poem.
이리 아첨하는 시라니
I'll let it pass, just barely.
그 정도면 간신히 합격이다
Thank you, Your Highness.
감사합니다, 세자
Write it down and compose a tune.
적어 두었다가 곡으로 만들어
Send it to Prince Changsha as a gift later.
나중에 장사왕께 바쳐라
Thank you, Your Highness.
감사합니다, 세자
Next one.
계속해라
With armored horses and spears, banners fluttered in the wind.
'철마와 창끝이 깃발을 휘날리고'
Brave warriors shed blood on the battlefield.
'용사들의 뜨거운 피가 전장을 물들이네'
The long wind brought rain like the tears of thousands of soldiers.
'거센 바람은 비가 되어 천군만마의 눈물이 되고'
Loyal souls from Jiuzhang Plain bowed towards their hometown.
'구장원의 충혼은 고향을 향해 절 하네'
Jiankang is so sunny and warm.
검강의 햇살은 참 따스하구나
Even now, the blood
이렇게 오래 흘렀는데
is still warm.
피가 아직도 따뜻하구나
Your Highness, do you know
전하께선
how cold the blood was in Jiuzhang Plain?
구장원의 피가 얼마나 차가운지 아십니까?
Do you know that the 18 coffins that entered the city
성안으로 들어온 18개의 관 속에는
actually contained 18 generals of my Beifu Army who died unjustly?
억울하게 죽은 18명의 북부군 장수가 있습니다
Actually, I don't care
사실 저는 당신들이
how you fight here in Jiankang at all.
검강에서 어떻게 싸우든 조금도 관심이 없습니다
I also don't care who sits on the throne,
황좌에 앉는 이가
whether it's you or His Majesty.
전하든 폐하든 그 또한 관심이 없습니다
But you made me change my mind.
하지만 전하께서 제 생각을 바꿔 놓으셨습니다
From today on,
오늘부터
you won't get anything you want, Prince Changsha.
장사왕께서 원하는 건 아무것도 얻지 못하실 겁니다
I'll snatch the person you want to marry.
전하께서 혼인하고 싶은 사람도 빼앗을 거고
And I will also take
이미 가진 것도
whatever you already have.
모두 빼앗을 겁니다
I was wrong. I was out of my mind.
제가 잘못했습니다 제가 정신이 나갔었습니다
Your Highness, you...
세자 저하...
Your Highness, you are a generous man.
세자 저하 너그러이 용서해 주십시오
I
본왕이
will chant sutras and pray for the fallen soldiers
매일 돌아가신 장수들을 위해
every day.
명복을 빌겠습니다
You still haven't found her?
아직도 못 찾았느냐?
Who on earth did she go to see?
대체 누굴 만나러 간 거야?
Mother!
어머니
-Mother. -Where on earth did you go?
- 어머니 - 대체 어디 간 거야?
I've just been to the restroom.
방금 뒷간에 다녀왔어요
Get in the carriage now. Let's go home.
어서 마차에 타거라 집으로 가자
Your Highness, it's anesthetic.
세자, 미약입니다
Go investigate the background
오늘 난대회에 나온
of all the stalls at today's Lantai gathering.
모든 노점을 조사해라
Any stalls with this mark
이 표식이 있는 곳은
belong to Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
모두 묘수 공자의 것이다
I'd like to know which family on earth she's from.
어느 집안 규수인지 한번 봐야겠어
[Prince Jing'an's Mansion]
[정안왕부]
Mother,
어머니
[Xiao Ziqi] [He Yuanji, Crown Princess in Prince Jing'an's family]
[소자기 정안왕부 세자빈, 하원희]
I am sleepy.
졸려요
[Xiao Yao, Prince Jing'an's eldest son; courtesy name: Anming]
[정안왕부 장자 소요 자, 안민]
He didn't even say anything
인사도 없이
and just sent a dozen coffins home.
관 열몇 개만 집으로 보냈습니다
[Yao Yunzhi, Prince Jing'an's consort]
[정안왕비, 요온지]
Anmin.
안민
Your Highness, Young Lord Xiao is back.
왕비 마마 세자께서 돌아오셨습니다
Where is he?
어디 있느냐?
His Highness took the dancers
세자께서 무희와
and Madam Rui back to Fuying Courtyard.
예씨 부인을 데리고 부영원으로 돌아가셨습니다
He said he'd rest early for the court tomorrow morning,
내일 조회가 있어 먼저 쉬신다고 하셨습니다
and he'd greet you, Your Highness, another day.
다음에 왕비 마마께 문안드리겠다고 전하셨습니다
Is this called resting early?
저게 쉬는 겁니까?
He is clearly having a party!
딱 봐도 연회를 벌인 거죠
That hurts like crazy.
아파 죽겠네
Keep messing around, and you'll never recover.
계속 이러시면 평생 못 나아요
[Ruisheng, maid who serves the Heir of Prince Jing'an]
[정안왕부 세자 시녀, 예생]
But I have you, right?
그래도 네가 있잖아
Even the best physician
아무리 용한 의원이라도
can't save a patient who seeks his death.
제 목숨 버리는 환자는 못 살려요
You barely survived this time.
이번엔 정말 구사일생이었어요
You must rest for half a year.
반년은 무조건 푹 쉬셔야 해요
Don't get worked up or fight.
화를 내서도 무예를 써서도 안 돼요
Once the injury relapses,
만약 상처가 다시 벌어지면
even gods can't save you.
신선이 와도 못 살려요
What I need to do can't be
내가 하려는 일은
put off for half a year.
반년이나 기다릴 수 없다
What are you going to do?
뭘 하려고요?
Young Lord Xiao, you've worked hard defending the territory these years
그간 소 세자가 국경을 지키느라 애썼고
and earned numerous military merits.
혁혁한 공을 세웠으니
You deserve a nice reward and promotion.
마땅히 후한 상을 내리고 작위를 높여 줘야겠다
You...
세자...
Thank you for your grace, Your Majesty.
태후마마의 은혜에 감사드립니다
I wouldn't dare decline the rewards for my soldiers.
장병들을 위한 포상은 감히 거절하지 않겠습니다
But for myself, I seek neither promotion nor titles.
하나 신은 벼슬도 작위도 바라지 않습니다
I only ask for one person.
오직 한 사람만을 원합니다
Please grant me this marriage, Your Majesty.
부디 태후마마께서 혼인을 윤허해 주십시오
I wish to marry
신은 정비의 예로
Grand Tutor Xie's daughter as my principal consort.
사 태부의 여식을 아내로 맞이하고 싶습니다